<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>What is Apache Flink? on Apache Flink</title>
    <link>//flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/</link>
    <description>Recent content in What is Apache Flink? on Apache Flink</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="//flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Architecture</title>
      <link>//flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/flink-architecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/flink-architecture/</guid>
      <description>What is Apache Flink? — Architecture # Apache Flink is a framework and distributed processing engine for stateful computations over unbounded and bounded data streams. Flink has been designed to run in all common cluster environments, perform computations at in-memory speed and at any scale.
Here, we explain important aspects of Flink&amp;rsquo;s architecture.
Process Unbounded and Bounded Data # Any kind of data is produced as a stream of events.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Applications</title>
      <link>//flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/flink-applications/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/flink-applications/</guid>
      <description>What is Apache Flink? — Applications # Apache Flink is a framework for stateful computations over unbounded and bounded data streams. Flink provides multiple APIs at different levels of abstraction and offers dedicated libraries for common use cases.
Here, we present Flink&amp;rsquo;s easy-to-use and expressive APIs and libraries.
Building Blocks for Streaming Applications # The types of applications that can be built with and executed by a stream processing framework are defined by how well the framework controls streams, state, and time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Operations</title>
      <link>//flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/flink-operations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/flink-operations/</guid>
      <description>What is Apache Flink? — Operations # Apache Flink is a framework for stateful computations over unbounded and bounded data streams. Since many streaming applications are designed to run continuously with minimal downtime, a stream processor must provide excellent failure recovery, as well as, tooling to monitor and maintain applications while they are running.
Apache Flink puts a strong focus on the operational aspects of stream processing. Here, we explain Flink&amp;rsquo;s failure recovery mechanism and present its features to manage and supervise running applications.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
