<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>About on Apache Flink</title>
    <link>https://flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/</link>
    <description>Recent content in About on Apache Flink</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Architecture</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/flink-architecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/flink-architecture/</guid>
      <description>What is Apache Flink? — Architecture # Apache Flink is a framework and distributed processing engine for stateful computations over unbounded and bounded data streams. Flink has been designed to run in all common cluster environments, perform computations at in-memory speed and at any scale.
Here, we explain important aspects of Flink&amp;rsquo;s architecture.
Process Unbounded and Bounded Data # Any kind of data is produced as a stream of events.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Applications</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/flink-applications/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/flink-applications/</guid>
      <description>What is Apache Flink? — Applications # Apache Flink is a framework for stateful computations over unbounded and bounded data streams. Flink provides multiple APIs at different levels of abstraction and offers dedicated libraries for common use cases.
Here, we present Flink&amp;rsquo;s easy-to-use and expressive APIs and libraries.
Building Blocks for Streaming Applications # The types of applications that can be built with and executed by a stream processing framework are defined by how well the framework controls streams, state, and time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Operations</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/flink-operations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/flink-operations/</guid>
      <description>What is Apache Flink? — Operations # Apache Flink is a framework for stateful computations over unbounded and bounded data streams. Since many streaming applications are designed to run continuously with minimal downtime, a stream processor must provide excellent failure recovery, as well as tooling to monitor and maintain applications while they are running.
Apache Flink puts a strong focus on the operational aspects of stream processing. Here, we explain Flink&amp;rsquo;s failure recovery mechanism and present its features to manage and supervise running applications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use Cases</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/use-cases/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/use-cases/</guid>
      <description>Use Cases # Apache Flink is an excellent choice to develop and run many different types of applications due to its extensive feature set. Flink&amp;rsquo;s features include support for stream and batch processing, sophisticated state management, event-time processing semantics, and exactly-once consistency guarantees for state. Moreover, Flink can be deployed on various resource providers such as YARN and Kubernetes, but also as a stand-alone cluster on bare-metal hardware. Configured for high availability, Flink does not have a single point of failure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Powered By</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/powered-by/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/powered-by/</guid>
      <description>Powered By Flink # Apache Flink powers business-critical applications in many companies and enterprises around the globe. On this page, we present a few notable Flink users that run interesting use cases in production and link to resources that discuss their applications in more detail.
More Flink users are listed in the Powered by Flink directory in the project wiki. Please note that the list is not comprehensive. We only add users that explicitly ask to be listed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roadmap</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/roadmap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/roadmap/</guid>
      <description>Roadmap # Preamble: This roadmap means to provide users and contributors with a high-level summary of ongoing efforts, grouped by the major threads to which the efforts belong. With so much that is happening in Flink, we hope that this helps with understanding the direction of the project. The roadmap contains both efforts in early stages as well as nearly completed efforts, so that users may get a better impression of the overall status and direction of those developments.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Community &amp; Project Info</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/community/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/community/</guid>
      <description>Community &amp;amp; Project Info # How do I get help from Apache Flink? # There are many ways to get help from the Apache Flink community. The mailing lists are the primary place where all Flink committers are present. For user support and questions use the user mailing list. You can also join the community on Slack. Some committers are also monitoring Stack Overflow. Please remember to tag your questions with the apache-flink tag.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Security</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/security/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/what-is-flink/security/</guid>
      <description>Security # Security Updates # This section lists fixed vulnerabilities in Flink.
CVE ID Affected Flink versions Notes CVE-2020-1960 1.1.0 to 1.1.5, 1.2.0 to 1.2.1, 1.3.0 to 1.3.3, 1.4.0 to 1.4.2, 1.5.0 to 1.5.6, 1.6.0 to 1.6.4, 1.7.0 to 1.7.2, 1.8.0 to 1.8.3, 1.9.0 to 1.9.2, 1.10.0 Users are advised to upgrade to Flink 1.9.3 or 1.10.1 or later versions or remove the port parameter from the reporter configuration (see advisory for details).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
