<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>How to Contribute on Apache Flink</title>
    <link>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/</link>
    <description>Recent content in How to Contribute on Apache Flink</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Overview</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/overview/</guid>
      <description>How To Contribute # Apache Flink is developed by an open and friendly community. Everybody is cordially welcome to join the community and contribute to Apache Flink. There are several ways to interact with the community and to contribute to Flink including asking questions, filing bug reports, proposing new features, joining discussions on the mailing lists, contributing code or documentation, improving the website, or testing release candidates.&#xA;What do you want to do?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contribute Code</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/contribute-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/contribute-code/</guid>
      <description>Contributing Code # Apache Flink is maintained, improved, and extended by code contributions of volunteers. We welcome contributions to Flink, but due to the size of the project and to preserve the high quality of the code base, we follow a contribution process that is explained in this document.&#xA;Please feel free to ask questions at any time. Either send a mail to the Dev mailing list or comment on the Jira issue you are working on.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Review Pull Requests</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/reviewing-prs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/reviewing-prs/</guid>
      <description>How to Review a Pull Request # This guide is for all committers and contributors that want to help with reviewing code contributions. Thank you for your effort - good reviews are one of the most important and crucial parts of an open source project. This guide should help the community to make reviews such that:&#xA;Contributors have a good contribution experience. Our reviews are structured and check all important aspects of a contribution.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Code Style and Quality Guide</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/code-style-and-quality-preamble/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/code-style-and-quality-preamble/</guid>
      <description>Apache Flink Code Style and Quality Guide # Preamble # Pull Requests &amp;amp; Changes # Common Coding Guide # Java Language Guide # Scala Language Guide # Components Guide # Formatting Guide # This is an attempt to capture the code and quality standard that we want to maintain.&#xA;A code contribution (or any piece of code) can be evaluated in various ways: One set of properties is whether the code is correct and efficient.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contribute Documentation</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/contribute-documentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/contribute-documentation/</guid>
      <description>Contribute Documentation # Good documentation is crucial for any kind of software. This is especially true for sophisticated software systems such as distributed data processing engines like Apache Flink. The Apache Flink community aims to provide concise, precise, and complete documentation and welcomes any contribution to improve Apache Flink&amp;rsquo;s documentation.&#xA;Obtain the documentation sources # Apache Flink&amp;rsquo;s documentation is maintained in the same git repository as the code base. This is done to ensure that code and documentation can be easily kept in sync.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Documentation Style Guide</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/documentation-style-guide/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/documentation-style-guide/</guid>
      <description>Documentation Style Guide # This guide provides an overview of the essential style guidelines for writing and contributing to the Flink documentation. It&amp;rsquo;s meant to support your contribution journey in the greater community effort to improve and extend existing documentation — and help make it more accessible, consistent and inclusive.&#xA;Language # The Flink documentation is maintained in US English and Chinese — when extending or updating the documentation, both versions should be addressed in one pull request.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contribute to the Website</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/improve-website/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/improve-website/</guid>
      <description>Improving the Website # The Apache Flink website presents Apache Flink and its community. It serves several purposes including:&#xA;Informing visitors about Apache Flink and its features. Encouraging visitors to download and use Flink. Encouraging visitors to engage with the community. We welcome any contribution to improve our website. This document contains all information that is necessary to improve Flink&amp;rsquo;s website.&#xA;Obtain the website sources # The website of Apache Flink is hosted in a dedicated git repository which is mirrored to GitHub at https://github.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Getting Help</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/getting-help/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/getting-help/</guid>
      <description>Getting Help # Having a Question? # The Apache Flink community answers many user questions every day. You can search for answers and advice in the archives or reach out to the community for help and guidance.&#xA;User Mailing List # Many Flink users, contributors, and committers are subscribed to Flink&amp;rsquo;s user mailing list. The user mailing list is a very good place to ask for help.&#xA;Before posting to the mailing list, you can search the mailing list archives for email threads that discuss issues related to yours on the following websites.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Code Style and Quality Guide — Common Rules</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/code-style-and-quality-common/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/code-style-and-quality-common/</guid>
      <description>Code Style and Quality Guide — Common Rules # Preamble # Pull Requests &amp;amp; Changes # Common Coding Guide # Java Language Guide # Scala Language Guide # Components Guide # Formatting Guide # 1. Copyright # Each file must include the Apache license information as a header.&#xA;/* * Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one * or more contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file * distributed with this work for additional information * regarding copyright ownership.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Code Style and Quality Guide — Components Guide</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/code-style-and-quality-components/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/code-style-and-quality-components/</guid>
      <description>Code Style and Quality Guide — Components Guide # Preamble # Pull Requests &amp;amp; Changes # Common Coding Guide # Java Language Guide # Scala Language Guide # Components Guide # Formatting Guide # Component Specific Guidelines # Additional guidelines about changes in specific components.&#xA;Configuration Changes # Where should the config option go?&#xA;‘flink-conf.yaml’: All configuration that pertains to execution behavior that one may want to standardize across jobs.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Code Style and Quality Guide — Formatting Guide</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/code-style-and-quality-formatting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/code-style-and-quality-formatting/</guid>
      <description>Code Style and Quality Guide — Formatting Guide # Preamble # Pull Requests &amp;amp; Changes # Common Coding Guide # Java Language Guide # Scala Language Guide # Components Guide # Formatting Guide # Java Code Formatting Style # We recommend to set up the IDE to automatically check the code style. Please follow the IDE Setup Guide to set up spotless and checkstyle .&#xA;License # Apache license headers.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Code Style and Quality Guide — Java</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/code-style-and-quality-java/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/code-style-and-quality-java/</guid>
      <description>Code Style and Quality Guide — Java # Preamble # Pull Requests &amp;amp; Changes # Common Coding Guide # Java Language Guide # Scala Language Guide # Components Guide # Formatting Guide # Java Language Features and Libraries # Preconditions and Log Statements # Never concatenate strings in the parameters Don’t: Preconditions.checkState(value &amp;lt;= threshold, &amp;quot;value must be below &amp;quot; + threshold) Don’t: LOG.debug(&amp;quot;value is &amp;quot; + value) Do: Preconditions.checkState(value &amp;lt;= threshold, &amp;quot;value must be below %s&amp;quot;, threshold) Do: LOG.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Code Style and Quality Guide — Pull Requests &amp; Changes</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/code-style-and-quality-pull-requests/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/code-style-and-quality-pull-requests/</guid>
      <description>Code Style and Quality Guide — Pull Requests &amp;amp; Changes # Preamble # Pull Requests &amp;amp; Changes # Common Coding Guide # Java Language Guide # Scala Language Guide # Components Guide # Formatting Guide # Rationale: We ask contributors to put in a little bit of extra effort to bring pull requests into a state that they can be more easily and more thoroughly reviewed. This helps the community in many ways:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Code Style and Quality Guide — Scala</title>
      <link>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/code-style-and-quality-scala/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flink.apache.org/how-to-contribute/code-style-and-quality-scala/</guid>
      <description>Code Style and Quality Guide — Scala # Preamble # Pull Requests &amp;amp; Changes # Common Coding Guide # Java Language Guide # Scala Language Guide # Components Guide # Formatting Guide # Scala Language Features # Where to use (and not use) Scala # We use Scala for Scala APIs or pure Scala Libraries.&#xA;We do not use Scala in the core APIs and runtime components. We aim to remove existing Scala use (code and dependencies) from those components.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
